Hello, and welcome to Lesson 37
你好，欢迎来到第37课
of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
的这个微积分导论与Wolfram U。
The topic for this lesson is separable differential equations.
本节课的课题是可分离微分方程。
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
我们先来简单介绍一下本课的内容。
The fact is that most differential equations cannot be solved easily.
事实上，大多数微分方程是不容易解决的。
For example, here’s a nonlinear equation.
例如，这里有一个非线性方程。
What I mean by that is that you’ve got y[x]^2 over here,
我的意思是，你已经得到y[x]^2在这里。
and DSolve can solve the equation, but the solution is rather messy
和DSolve可以解方程，但解法比较乱。
and involves these so-called Bessel functions,
并涉及这些所谓的贝塞尔函数。
which occur in the oscillations of drums and elsewhere.
在鼓和其他地方的振荡中出现的。
In contrast to that, there are other equations
与此相反，还有其他方程
where you actually can find a simple solution.
在这里，你其实可以找到一个简单的解决方案。
Here’s an example where the solution is quite simple,
这里有一个例子，解决方法很简单。
and if you look over here, in part it’s because
如果你看这里，部分原因是由于。
the differential equation itself is a bit simpler.
微分方程本身就比较简单。
This is an example of a separable differential equation.
这是一个可分离微分方程的例子。
The theme of this lesson is to talk about
本节课的主题是谈谈
these separable differential equations.
这些可分离的微分方程。
The question is what is a separable differential equation?
问题是什么是可分离微分方程？
Well, a separable differential equation is
那么，一个可分离的微分方程就是
an equation of the form y', the derivative of y,
形式为y'的方程，即y的导数。
equal to some function of x times some function of y.
等于x乘以y的某个函数。
Okay. Now if you look at this,
好吧，如果你看看这个现在，如果你看看这个。
the right-hand side is certainly what you’d call separable.
右手边肯定是你所说的可分离的。
You can separate x and y.
你可以把x和y分开。
The question is how about the left-hand side?
问题是左手边怎么样？
Well, recall that y' is dy/dx,
好吧，回忆一下，y'就是dy/dx。
so we can think of that as a separation for y'.
所以我们可以把它看作是y'的分离。
For example, here is the differential equation
例如，以下是微分方程
that we spoke about in an earlier slide, and if you want to solve it,
我们在前面的幻灯片中讲到的，如果你想解决它。
you replace y' by dy/dx
您用dy/dx代替y'。
and then you separate your variables like over here.
然后你把你的变量分开，就像这里。
You have (1/y)dy = xdx like you do in algebra.
你有(1/y)dy=xdx，就像在代数中那样。
Then you integrate both the sides.
然后你把两边整合起来。
Then you say that this y is e^(C + (x^2/2)),
那么你说这个y就是e^(C+(x^2/2))。
but that’s the same as e^C * e^(x^2/2),
但这和e^C*e^(x^2/2)一样。
and then that itself with e^C
然后，它本身与e^C。
is another constant which we will call K.
是另一个常数，我们称之为K。
The solution is y equal to some constant times e^(x^2/2).
解为y等于某个常数倍e^(x^2/2)。
That is the general solution of the differential equation.
这就是微分方程的一般解。
Okay. On to another example.
好吧，再举一个例子。在另一个例子。
Let’s try and solve the differential equation y' = y.
让我们试着解微分方程y'=y。
In this case, you can think of f[x] = 1 and g[y] = y,
在这种情况下，你可以认为f[x]=1，g[y]=y。
so that’s the separation of the right-hand side.
所以这就是右侧的分离。
Keep in mind that y' is dy/dx, so you separate your variables,
请记住，y'是dy/dx，所以你要分开你的变量。
rearrange and you get dy/y = 1dx.
重新排列后得到dy/y=1dx。
Then you integrate both sides.
然后你把两边整合起来。
I haven’t put the constant, but it’s certainly there in the background.
我没有放常量，但后台肯定是有的。
So y is e^(x + C) where C is a constant,
所以y是e^(x+C)，其中C是一个常数。
so you get e^C * e^x.
所以你得到e^C * e^x。
That’s K * e^x.
那就是K * e^x。
You can confirm the answer with DSolveValue,
你可以用DSolveValue来确认答案。
and you get back just the same result.
而你得到的只是同样的结果。
Okay. On to a slightly harder example
好吧，那就举个稍微难一点的例子吧。再举一个稍微难一点的例子
where you have y' = 3x^3/(4y + Sin[y]).
其中你有y'=3x^3/(4y+Sin[y])。
In this case, f is just the numerator,
在这种情况下，f只是分子。
and for g, you can take 1 over the denominator.
而对于g，可以在分母上取1。
That’s the differential equation,
这就是微分方程。
and then you separate the variables and rearrange.
然后你把变量分开，重新排列。
Integrate both the sides separately, and now we see that
将两边分别整合，现在我们看到的是
the solution is going to be 2y^2 – Cos[y] = (3x^4)/4 + C.
解为2y^2 - Cos[y] = (3x^4)/4 + C。
Here is a plot of the solution with ContourPlot.
下面是用ContourPlot绘制的解决方案。
Okay. The question is what happens when there are initial values?
好吧，问题是当有初始值时，会发生什么？问题是当有初始值时会发生什么？
Let’s take the equation y' = x * y
让我们用公式y'=x*y。
with the initial condition y[0] = 1.
与初始条件y[0]=1。
That’s an initial value problem with a value of y given at 0.
这是一个初值问题，在0处给出y的值。
The question is can you then find a particular solution
问题是你能不能找到一个特定的解决方案
of this differential equation?
这个微分方程的?
Let’s rearrange the equation as earlier.
让我们按照前面的公式重新排列。
Solve it, so you get y equal to K, where K is a constant,
解，所以得到y等于K，其中K是一个常数。
times e^(x^2/2).
乘以e^(x^2/2)。
Now we plug in the initial values.
现在我们插入初始值。
You get y[0] = 1, so you get 1 = K * e^0, so K = 1.
得到y[0]=1，所以得到1=K*e^0，所以K=1。
The solution is y = e^(x^2/2).
解为y=e^(x^2/2)。
You can confirm that with DSolve.
你可以用DSolve来确认。
You can also check the solution plot by doing a StreamPlot.
你也可以通过做一个StreamPlot来检查溶液图。
Okay. On to some applications, and we’ll take two of them.
好的，我知道了在一些应用程序， 我们将采取其中的两个。
The first one is for current.
第一个是针对电流。
Here’s an equation that describes a circuit
这里有一个描述电路的公式。
in which there’s some charge flowing, some resistance,
在其中有一些电荷流动，一些电阻。
some capacitance and some voltage—that’s supposed to be circuit.
一些电容和一些电压，这应该是电路。
That’s the equation, the differential equation, for the charge q.
这就是电荷q的方程，微分方程。
Now of course if v depends on t, that’s much harder,
现在当然如果v取决于t，那就更难了。
so we’ll assume that v itself is a constant,
所以我们假设v本身是一个常数。
so we’ve got constant resistance, capacitance and voltage.
所以我们有恒定的电阻、电容和电压。
In that situation where v does not depend upon t,
在这种情况下，v不取决于t。
you can solve for q', and then you see that
你可以解出q'，然后你会看到
things are separable over here.
这里的东西是可以分开的。
You separate the equation and get an expression for t
你分开方程，得到t的表达式。
in terms of everything else, but we want to solve for q.
但我们想求解q。
You solve for q.
你求解q。
The Normal here just means you’re ignoring some conditions on q.
这里的Normal只是意味着你忽略了q上的一些条件。
The solution is c times v
解为c乘以v。
minus e raised to that expression over there,
减去e提高到那边的表达。
but if you think about this, it’s really e^(–k/c) * e^(–t/r).
但如果你仔细想想，其实就是e^(-k/c) * e^(-t/r)。
That’s just K * e^–t(c * r).
那只是K * e^-t(c * r)。
One final point.
最后一点。
As the time approaches ∞ as more and more time goes by,
随着时间的接近∞随着时间的推移越来越多。
the value of e^–∞ = 0, so this term, drops out,
e^-∞的值=0，所以这个项，掉了。
and the final solution is that the charge approaches c * v
而最终的解决方案是，电荷量接近c*v。
as t approaches ∞.
当t接近∞时。
A second example is for Newton’s law of cooling.
第二个例子是针对牛顿冷却定律。
Here is a differential equation for the temperature
下面是一个温度的微分方程。
when an object at temperature t0 initially is placed in a medium
当一个温度t0的物体最初被放置在一个介质中时。
where the temperature is held constant at s.
其中温度在s时保持不变。
What happens is that the rate of change of temperature
发生的情况是，温度的变化率。
is proportional to the difference between the current temperature
与当前温度的差值成正比。
and the temperature of the surroundings.
和周围环境的温度。
As time goes by and the difference becomes small,
随着时间的流逝，差别变得很小。
the rate falls down as well.
率也随之下降。
You need to determine k.
你需要确定k。
We’re given the initial condition that the temperature at 0 is t0.
我们给出的初始条件是0处的温度为t0。
Now of course over here we have a separable equation,
当然，在这里我们有一个可分离的方程。
so you separate the variables and you get back
所以你把变量分开，然后你就会得到
an expression for t in terms of temperature,
用温度表示t的表达式；
but you want to solve for temperature,
但你要解决温度问题。
so you do that and you get an answer.
所以你这样做，你会得到一个答案。
Now the point is that e^(c * k) is a constant,
现在的问题是，e^(c*k)是一个常数。
so again you can call that some c and you solve for that constant.
所以你又可以把它叫做一些c，你就可以求解这个常数。
The final solution is that the solution for the temperature at time t
最后的解是，时间t时的温度的解。
is (–s + t0)e^(k * t) + s.
是(-s+t0)e^(k*t)+s。
You can check the answer with DSolve,
你可以用DSolve检查答案。
and you get back the same expression.
而你得到的是同样的表情。
Now the question is how to determine k.
现在的问题是如何确定k。
To find k, what you need is the temperature t1 at some later time τ.
要找到k，你需要的是以后某个时间τ的温度t1。
Suppose we know that temperature.
假设我们知道，温度。
Then we plug the values in into the solution
然后我们将这些值插入到解决方案中
and you solve for k, and that is the expression for k.
而你解出k，这就是k的表达式。
The constant k is Log[(s – t1)/(s – t0)]/τ.
常数k为Log[(s-t1)/(s-t0)]/τ。
As an application, let’s say you have got
作为一个应用，比如说你已经有了
a cup of boiling coffee at 100 ºC.
一杯100℃的沸腾咖啡。
It’s boiling.
它的沸腾。
You put it in a room in which the temperature is 22 ºC.
你把它放在温度为22℃的房间里。
Let’s say an hour later, the temperature of the coffee is 60 ºC.
假设一个小时后，咖啡的温度是60 ºC。
Then what you can do is you can model the coffee temperature
那么你可以做的是你可以模拟咖啡的温度。
by the equation over here where I’ve plugged in the value of k
由这里的公式，我已经插入了k的值。
based on the given information.
根据给定的信息。
That is the starting temperature, that’s the room temperature,
那是起始温度，那是室温。
and you want to model the coffee over a period of time.
而你想在一段时间内对咖啡进行建模。
Let’s see what happens to it over a period of, let’s say, 10 hours.
让我们看看10小时后会发生什么。
You can see that the temperature slowly approaches
你可以看到，温度慢慢接近
the room temperature, which is 22, and in fact,
的室温，即22，事实上。
you can use Limit to check that the answer is actually 22
你可以用Limit来检查答案实际上是22。
when you have let infinitely many hours pass by.
当你让无限的时间流逝。
That’s Newton’s law which models the cooling of objects
这就是牛顿定律，它是物体冷却的模型。
which are placed in a room with a higher temperature
放在温度较高的房间里。
than room temperature.
比室温。
Okay. That brings me to the end of this lesson,
好了，我的课就到此结束了。本课到此结束。
and the main point is that separable equations are,
而最主要的是，可分离方程是。
in general, rather easy to solve.
一般来说，相当容易解决。
The way that you solve them is to note that
你解决它们的方法是注意以下几点
the right-hand side is a function of x times a function of y,
右边是x乘以y的函数。
and then you can replace y' by differentials dy and dx
然后你可以用差分dy和dx来代替y'。
and then solve the equation.
然后解方程。
Now of course you can use that to model the various phenomena.
现在你当然可以用它来模拟各种现象。
For example, you can model the charge in a circuit
例如，你可以对电路中的电荷进行建模。
by a separable differential equation,
由一个可分离微分方程。
or you can model the temperature over time for a hot object
或者你可以为一个热物体建立温度随时间变化的模型。
using separable differential equations.
使用可分离微分方程。
In the next lesson, we’ll talk about how we can make programs
在下一课中，我们将讨论如何使程序成为
that help to solve calculus problems
帮助解决微积分问题
when doing differential equations.
做微分方程时。
But before that, do revise today’s lesson.
不过在这之前，先把今天的课做一下修改。
It’s quite an important topic, separable differential equations.
这是一个相当重要的话题，可分离微分方程。
I’ll see you in the next lesson.
下节课见。
Thank you very much. I’ll stop over here.
谢谢你了我会在这里停下来。